John Fleming Gould Papers
John Fleming Gould Papers
1925-1965
Gould, John Fleming
12 linear ft.
Tear sheets, posters, etc. from the American artist
5203335
Biographical History
John Fleming Gould (1906-1996) was an American painter, illustrator, and art instructor.
Born in Worcester, Massachusetts, Gould studied at Pratt Institute in Brooklyn. His illustrations appeared in national publications such as the Saturday Evening Post as well as pulp publications such as Adventure Trails, Dime Detective Magazine, and War Birds, while his fine art pieces -- watercolors and oil paintings -- often portray historical subjects and the Hudson River Valley area.
For more than twenty years, Gould was an art consultant for General Electric Company's Locomotive Division, producing hundreds of illustrations for their corporate publications and advertising. He also taught at Pratt Institute for 22 years. In 1957, he and his wife Mary established the Bethlehem Art Gallery in Cornwall, New York.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Fleming Gould Papers consists of orginal artwork, illustrations created for General Electric (GE) and for a wide range of pulp magazines, and a few scrapbooks and other items of memorabilia.
Art, original contains pencil sketches by Gould. Most have themes reminiscent of his pulp illustrations, but the largest is a group scene of men and women in fine clothes, evidently at a party. The latter, with its turquoise accents on flowers and one woman's dress, is also the only piece with some color.
General Electric posters contains nearly 200 "Progress Posters" created for the company between 1957 and 1965, for use in schools and colleges. For many years, GE's corporate slogan was "Progress is our Most Important Product." At the end of this series are few other GE posters, two from a series highlighting challenges GE was tackling.
Pulp illustrations form the largest part of the collection, with more than 3000 tear sheets of Gould's illustrations for pulp magazines from the 1920s through the 1940s. In addition to adventure magazines like Adventure Trails, Danger Trail, and Sky Riders, titles represented include crime/detective (All Detective Magazine, Clues, Detective Action), "flying pulps" (Air Adventures, Flying Stories, Wings), mobster stories (Gang World, Underworld Romances), science fiction (Astounding Stories), westerns (Cowboy Stories, Dime Western Magazine), and World War II (Battle Aces, War Birds, War Stories).
Scrapbooks and other memorabilia contains an article from the Miami Herald about Robert Hogan, writer of the Battle Aces series, a few biographical items matted together, and four scrapbooks of Gould's GE and pulp illustration work.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically by type or title. Pulp tear sheets are arranged alphabetically by magazine title and, within that, alphabetically by story title.
Related Material
has numerous collections and cataloged items relating to early pulp magazines, including the
Street & Smith Records
. Please for relevant manuscript material, and refer to to locate issues of pulp magazines and other published items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Painters; Popular culture; Gould, John Fleming.; General Electric Company.; Adventure stories, American -- Periodicals.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Artists -- United States.; Commercial art.; Detective and mystery stories, American -- Periodicals.; Illustrators -- United States.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American.; Popular culture -- United States.; Popular literature -- United States.; Pulp literature, American -- Illustrations.; Science fiction, American -- Periodicals.; Spy stories -- Periodicals.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Periodicals.; Western stories -- Periodicals.; Clippings (information artifacts); Posters.; Tear sheets.; Scrapbooks.; Sketches.; Artists.; Illustrators.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert Gould, 2019.
Inventory
- Art, original
  - Cowboy, back view, gun drawn, pencil sketch (Oversize 1)
  - Cowboy, leaning on post, pencil sketch (Oversize 1)
  - Cowboy, front view, two-fisted, pencil sketch (Oversize 2)
  - Cowboy, sitting in chair, pencil sketch (Oversize 2)
  - Group of men and women in dress clothes, pencil and watercolor (Oversize 14)
  - Man in pain, pencil sketch (Oversize 3)
  - Man grabbing victim, pencil sketch (Oversize 3)
  - Man with flashlight, pencil sketch (Oversize 4)
  - Man standing, 1936; pencil sketch (Oversize 5)
  - Woman seated, 1936; pencil sketch (Oversize 5)
- General Electric posters
  - Progress Posters, list with dates and titles (provided by donor) (Box 1)
  - Progress Posters, 1957-1958 (Oversize 6)
  - Progress Posters, 1959-1960 (Oversize 7)
  - Progress Posters, 1961-1962 (Oversize 8)
  - Progress Posters, 1963-1964 (Oversize 9)
  - Progress Posters, 1965 (Oversize 10)
  - Progress Posters, duplicates, 1 Jan 1961; 15 Jan 1961;; 15 Feb 1961;; 15 Feb 1963;; 1 Dec 1964; 5 items (Oversize 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Oversize 10)
    "Charles Steinmetz, the electrical genius who tamed lightning," GE #648
    Challenge: How to tame power on the loose in a vacuum
    Challenge: How to help Navajos carve a new future
- Pulp illustrations
  - Book frontispieces (Box 1)
  - Proofs, unidentified (Box 1)
  - Tear sheets
    - Ace high magazine (Box 1)
    - Aces (Box 1)
    - Adventure trails (Box 1)
    - Air adventures (Box 1)
    - Air stories (Box 1)
    - All detective magazine (Box 1)
    - Astounding stories (Box 1)
    - Battle aces, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Blue book magazine, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Brief stories (Box 1)
    - Clues (Box 1)
    - Complete detective novel magazine (Box 1)
    - Cowboy stories (Box 1)
    - Danger trail (Box 1)
    - Detective action, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Dime detective magazine, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Dime mystery book magazine (Box 2)
    - Dime western magazine (Box 2)
    - Dime sports magazine (Box 2)
    - Flying stories (Box 2)
    - Gang world, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Illustrated adventure trails (Box 2)
    - Sky riders (Box 2)
    - Ten detective aces (Box 2)
    - Three star magazine (Box 3)
    - Three star stories (Box 3)
    - Underworld love stories (Box 3)
    - Underworld romances (Box 3)
    - War aces (Box 3)
    - War birds, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - War stories, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Western rangers, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Western romances (Box 3)
    - Western trails (Box 3)
    - Wide world adventures, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Wild west stories and complete novel magazine (Box 3)
    - Wings (Box 3)
    - Unidentified, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks and other memorabilia
  - Article, "G-8: Spy King of the Pulps," Miami Herald, 8 Jul 1962; about author Robert J. Hogan, with mention of Gould (Oversize 5)
  - Biographical sketch and photographs, matted (Oversize 5)
  - Scrapbooks
    - GE posters (Oversize 11)
    - Mirror sketches for pulps, 1927-1931 (Oversize 12)
    - Pulp tear sheets (Oversize 12)
    - Sample illustrations, 1931-1936 (Oversize 13)